Aleksinskii, Grigorii, b. 1879. Grigorii Aleksinskii papers, 1895-1913 (MS Russ 73): Guide.
Grigorii Aleksinskii papers,
1895-1913.
Houghton Library, Harvard College Library, Harvard University
MS Russ 73
Aleksinskii, Grigorii, b. 1879.
1 box (.3 linear ft.)
Papers relating to pre-revolutionary Russian Socialist activities, especially pertaining to Russian Social Democrat Gregorii Aleksinskii and his associates.
Transferred from the Widener Library purchase of the Gregorii Aleksinskii archive of books and manuscripts; received: 1964 Nov.
There are no restrictions on physical access to this material.
Aleksinskii (1879-1967) was an author, a pre-revolutionary Russian Social Democrat, an Otzovist after the 1905 revolution, and a one-time member of the 2nd Duma of 1907 from Petrograd. During the 1917 revolution, he joined Plekhanov's Yedinstvo Group, and after July, was a counter-revolutionary opposing the Bolsheviks. He was also an author of forgeries against Lenin. In April 1918 he emigrated to France and joined the counter-revolutionary organization of General Wrangel.
12 items including materials by: A. Bogdanov (Malinovskii), S. Semkovskii (Bronshtein), A.I. Chuprov, P.B. Struve, and S.IU. Vitte; materials relating to the Russian Social Democratic Schools on Capri and Bologna, possible V.I. Lenin letter forgery, V.I. Lenin typescripts with manuscript corrections, proofs of work by G.V. Plekhanov, letter to the "Vpered" group of Social Democrats, and other items.
A major archive of Aleksinskii papers is housed at the Bakhmeteff Archive at Columbia University in New York City.
- [Semkovskii, S.] Philosophiia marksizma (Dialektich. mat.): AMsS (by Semkovskii), Capri, Italy, 1909., (1); 3s.(6p.) in 1 folder.
  Lecture delivered at the Vysshaia sotsial-demokraticheskaia propagandistsko-agitatorskaia shkola dlia rabochikh (1st: 1909: Capri, Italy).
  Possibly in the hand of Semen Iul'evich Bronshtein [Semkovskii].
- Chuprov, A.I. (Aleksandr Ivanovich), 1842-1908. Vliianie urozhaev i khlebnykh tsen na raznyia storony ekonomicheskoi zhizni. Doklad Prof. A.I. Chuprova i preniia v III otdelenii Imperatorskago vol'nago ekonomicheskago obshchestva: printed pamphlet, St. Petersburg, 1897., (2); [iv], 95p. and a folded chart in 1 folder.
  With printed gray wrappers.
  Contains pencilled marginal notes and underlinings possibly by V.I. Lenin.
  Titled: The influence of the harvest and of wheat prices on various facets of economic life.
- Lenin, Vladimir Il'ich, 1870-1924. Ms letter (in unidentified hand) to ?; [n.p., 1908]., (3); 1s.(2p.) in 1 folder.
  With a typed copy.
  A note of G.A. Aleksinskii on this letter reads: "Kopiia etogo (neizdannogo) pis'ma byla sobstvennoruchno aniato G.A. Aleksinskim s vedoma i razresheniia g-zhi X."
  Richard Pipes says this is a forgery 4-9-1969.
- Lenin, Vladimir Il'ich, 1870-1924. Typescript letter (unsigned) to Vysshaia sotsial-demokraticheskaia propagandistsko-agitatorskaia shkola dlia rabochikh (1st: 1909: Capri, Italy); [n.p.], 1909 Aug. 18., (4); 2s.(2p.) in 1 folder.
  This letter appears also in the broadside issued by the school, titled "K voprosu o partiinoi shkole (chetyre dokuments)."
- Lenin, Vladimir Il'ich, 1870-1924. Typescript letter (unsigned) to students of the Vysshaia sotsial-demokraticheskaia propagandistsko-agitatorskaia shkola dlia rabochikh (1st: 1909: Capri, Italy); [n.p.], 1909 Aug. 30., (5); 5s.(5p.) in 1 folder.
- Lenin, Vladimir Il'ich, 1870-1924. Staryi proekt partiinoi programmy (1896 goda): typescript with AMs corrections, [n.p.], 1896., (6); 5s.(5p.) in 1 folder.
  This text most closely resembles that first collected in V.I. Lenin, Sobranie sochinenii, vol. 1, pp. 281-285. For details about the publication of the two known variant texts, see Khronologicheskii ukazatel' proizvedenii V.I. Lenina 56.
- [Bogdanov, A. (Aleksandr), 1873-1928. 3 hectographed lectures delivered at the Vysshaia sotsial-demokraticheskaia propagandistsko-agitatorskaia shkola dlia rabochikh (1st: 1909: Capri, Italy); 1909., (7); 3 folders.
  By Aleksandr Aleksandrovich Malinovskii [Bodganov].
- Plekhanov, Georgii Valentinovich, 1856-1918. Nashi raznoglasiia; chast vtoraia Zheneva, Tip. gruppy Osvobozhdeniia truda: proof sheets with AMs revisions, Geneva, 1895., (8); 14f.(26p.) in 1 folder.
  The introduction, pp.[3]-7 was apparently never published. Pp. [9]-32 were published, with many revisions, as pp. [82]-115 of Obosnovanie narodnichestva v trudakh g-na Vorontsova (V.V.); kriticheskii etiud (St. Petersburg, 1896).
  Titled: Our differences; part two.
- SDKPiL. Ms letter (signed by a secretary) for the Social Democratic Grupa "Vpered": Paris, 1913 May 15., (9); 1s.(2p.) in 1 folder.
  From the Sotsial'demokratii Pol'shi i Litvy, biuro zagranichnykh grupp.
- Vysshaia sotsial-demokraticheskaia propagandistsko-agitatorskaia shkola dlia rabochikh (1st: 1909: Capri, Italy). 7 Ms compositions, 1909., (10); 1 folder.
  Papers written by various students at the school.
- Vysshaia sotsial-demokraticheskaia propagandistsko-agitatorskaia shkola dlia rabochikh (1st: 1909: Capri, Italy). 11 Ms and hectographed documents, 1909., (11); 1 folder.
  Also includes document pertaining to the Vysshaia sotsial-demokraticheskaia propagandistsko-agitatorskaia shkola dlia rabochikh (2nd: 1910-1911: Bologna, Italy).
- Vitte, S. IU. (Sergei IUl'evich), graf, 1849-1915. Samoderzhavie i zemstvo. Konfidentsial'naia zapiska ministra finansov stats-sekretaria S. Iu. Vitte (1899 g.) Vtoroe izdanie s dvumia predisloviiami Petra Struve i s prilozheniem zapiski ministra finansov o napriazhenii platezhnykh sil naseleniia: printed pamphlet, Stuttgart, J.H.W. Dietz, 1903., (12); 1xxii, 224p. in 1 folder.
  With printed brown wrappers.
  Petr Berngardovich Struve's prefaces have pencilled marginal notes and underlinings possibly by Vladimir Il'ich Lenin.
  Titled: Autocracy and the zemstvo; a confidential memoir.